Baked or fried,
boiled /bɔɪld/ or roasted,
as chips or fries.
At some point in your life,
you've probably eaten a potato.
Delicious, for sure,
but the fact is potatoes have played a
much more significant role in our history
than just that of the dietary /ˈdaɪətərɪ 膳食de/ staple /ˈsteɪpəl 主食 订书钉/
we have come to know and love today.
Without the potato,
our modern civilization
might not exist at all.
8,000 years ago in South America,
high atop /əˈtɒp 在顶上/ the Andes,
ancient /ˈeɪnʃənt/ Peruvians were the first
to cultivate the potato.
Containing high levels of proteins
and carbohydrates /ˌkɑːbəʊˈhaɪdreɪts 碳水化合物食品/,
as well as essential fats, vitamins
and minerals /ˈmɪnərəl 矿物/,
potatoes were the perfect food source
to fuel a large Incan /ˈɪŋkən 印加人/ working class
as they built and farmed
their terraced /ˈtɛrəs 梯田/ fields,
mined the Rocky Mountains,
and created the sophisticated /səˈfistikeit 弄复杂/ civilization
of the great Incan Empire /ˈempaɪə/.
But considering how vital /ˈvaɪtəl 必不可少的/ they were
to the Incan people,
when Spanish sailors
returning from the Andes
first brought potatoes to Europe,
the spuds /spʌd 马铃薯/ were duds /dʌd 无用的/.
Europeans simply didn't want to eat
what they considered dull /dʌl 枯燥乏味/ and tasteless
oddities /ˈɒdɪtɪ 古怪/ from a strange new land,
too closely related to the deadly
nightshade /ˈnaɪtˌʃeɪd 龙葵属植物/ plant belladonna /ˌbɛləˈdɒnə 颠茄/ for comfort.
So instead of consuming them,
they used potatoes
as decorative garden plants.
More than 200 years would pass
before the potato caught on
as a major food source throughout Europe,
though even then,
it was predominantly /prɪˈdɒmɪnəntlɪ 主要地/ eaten
by the lower classes.
However, beginning around 1750,
and thanks at least in part
to the wide availability /əveiləbiliti/
of inexpensive and nutritious /njuːˈtrɪʃəs/ potatoes,
European peasants  /ˈpezənt 农民/
with greater food security
no longer found themselves
at the mercy /ˈmɜːsɪ 宽恕/ of the regularly
occurring grain /ɡreɪn 谷物/ famines /ˈfæmɪn 饥荒/ of the time,
and so their populations steadily /stedəli 稳定地/ grew.
As a result, the British, Dutch /dʌtʃ 荷兰人/
and German Empires
rose on the backs of the growing groups
of farmers, laborers /ˈleɪbərə 工人/, and soldiers,
thus lifting the West to its place
of world dominion /dəˈmɪnjən 主权，统治/.
However, not all European countries
sprouted /spraʊt 发芽/ empires.
After the Irish /ˈaɪrɪʃ 爱尔兰/ adopted the potato,
their population dramatically increased,
as did their dependence on the tuber /ˈtjuːbə 块茎/
as a major food staple /ˈsteɪpəl/.
But then disaster struck /strʌk 打击/.
From 1845 to 1852,
potato blight /blaɪt 疫病；枯病/ disease ravaged /ˈrævɪdʒ 重创/
the majority of Ireland's /ˈaɪələnd/ potato crop,
leading to the Irish Potato Famine /ˈfæmɪn 饥荒/,
one of the deadliest famines /ˈfæmɪn 饥荒/
in world history.
Over a million Irish citizens
starved to death,
and 2 million more
left their homes behind.
But of course, this wasn't the end
for the potato.
The crop eventually recovered,
and Europe's population,
especially the working classes,
continued to increase.
Aided by the influx /ˈɪnˌflʌks 汇集/ of Irish migrants /ˈmaɪɡrənt/,
Europe now had a large, sustainable,
and well-fed population
who were capable of manning /ˈmænɪŋ 配备人员/
the emerging factories
that would bring about our modern world
via /ˈvaɪə/ the Industrial Revolution.
So it's almost impossible to imagine
a world without the potato.
Would the Industrial Revolution
ever have happened?
Would World War II have been lost
by the Allies /ælaiz/
without this easy-to-grow crop
that fed the Allied troops?
Would it even have started?
When you think about it like this,
many major milestones in world history
can all be at least partially /ˈpɑːʃəli 部分地/ attributed /əˈtrɪbjuːt 属性/
to the simple spud /spʌd 马铃薯/
from the Peruvian /pəˈruːviən 秘鲁人/ hilltops.